[Music]
hey hey welcome back so today is day
three I learn it about
Tinkercad today what we're going to be
working with is programming with code so
we're gonna be using code to do some
things and we're just going to kind of
have some fun we're gonna do some some
kind of advanced things we're gonna work
with an LCD screen and some servos and
write some code as always I'm here with
my my trusty camper McKinlay you ready
to go today mckinley yes alright let's
see what we're after today so today
we're going to be playing with an LCD
that stands for a liquid crystal display
and servo motors and we're gonna be
writing some code I've got breadboard
that I just built up with the the
example in here now what my screen is
doing and what my breadboard of doing
are kind of like different stages of the
project this stage is where you turn the
potentiometer to turn the servo motor
almost no way you can see the servo
motor that that well but who knows
cameras are really good these days so as
I turn this potentiometer it's gonna
turn the servo motor you can also see if
you can see the LCD screen that it's
showing you what the potentiometer
reading is and then also the number of
degrees of the servo motor so that's
what we're after today is to learn about
potentiometers analog readings LCD
screens all kinds of fun stuff so what
you're going to need to do is you're
going to need to go back to your
tinkerer dashboard Tinkercad
make sure you're not in 3d designs
you're in your circuits area and we're
going to create a new circuit together
so go and click on create new circuit
hopefully you've kind of played around
with some things in Tinkercad and maybe
you've broken a thing or two but that's
okay it's it's all it's all for learning
that's that's part of the maker spirit
so the first thing I'm going to do today
to start things off is I'm gonna rename
my project I'm gonna call it fun with
LCDs and servo motors now normally what
we've done
to start things off is we've added a
breadboard and then we've also added an
Arduino Uno
uh what's clicking on them just to kind
of show you what they were about I don't
actually want to add them yet but today
what we're gonna teach you a little bit
about is the the starter projects so
where it says components basics switch
it to say starters I don't tell you what
to say starters all so components are
individual pieces and then you build
them up to make things but starters are
neat little circuits that you can just
kind of like bring over and see like a
whole big thing right so I mean I'm
tempted to like bring over a whole bunch
of them starters are fun right like you
could definitely spend the better part
of an afternoon just look in different
starters so this is not the starter that
we're going to do today but this is LEDs
that are connected to an RGB LED at the
top all kinds of different things you
could do right so that was just kind of
an example to start remember to undo
hopefully that just goes away
but I can go through here and I could
play with all these different starters
I'm like I'm tempted to do em all right
this one is a proximity sensor that was
Sora's and so when things move in the
field of vision the LED goes off so fun
to play with these things but today the
one that we're looking for is the one
that has an LCD screen on it so go down
through the scores until you kind of see
one all these looks so fun until you see
one with an LCD screen on it there it is
there's LCD and let's go ahead and drag
it over you can drag it over or the way
Tinkercad works best is I think if you
click on it then click again it pops
over it does take it just a second to
pop over so don't like touch anything
loads bringing it over and so the nice
thing about this is they did a bunch of
the wiring for an LCD for us which is
nice wiring up an LCD there's a standard
protocol for it it's not hard I'll talk
about it just a little bit but I mean I
I wired up my physical one here you
could totally do it it just takes a lot
of wires I'm gonna describe the most
important parts of it so the most
important parts of it there's power and
ground to the LCD those are the first
two actually is ground then power the
next one is your contrast pin so I've
got my contrast pin set up over here and
all the contrast pin what you do is it
lets you change the text of like how
much contrast there is in your LCD right
and so it's very useful on a real
circuit but in Tinkercad it's not that
important right and then after that
there's seven different control lines so
here's one two I guess this one's just
grounded three four five and six I guess
that was my seventh that was grounded
there and then there's a backlight on it
which is just an LED which is on here so
really it's just power ground a contrast
7 control lines of which one of which is
grounded and then a backlight and then
in your code so let's go and look at the
code that they added for this guy
you'll notice that the code here jumped
straight into text and that's because
like with blocks it's kind of annoying
to do this this code right so let's go
ahead and glance at this code and kind
of figure out what's on here so the
first part of this code is what's called
a comment so everything that's kind of
like light gray here is a comment now
comments are all long good it gives
credit to the authors and things like
that but I kind of don't want so I'm
just gonna delete all the comments just
because it'll make my code a little bit
cleaner the next comment is another
style of comment this is a slash slash
again it's kind of this brown color
anything that's a brown color is just a
comment I can get deleted now you do
have to be careful when you're deleting
that you don't want to just kind of get
haphazard with the leading and delete
things that are that are not comments
but it's a it's a comma here I'm gonna
see if I can make my font a little bit
bigger for here maybe if I do this it'll
look bigger that works and so we're
going to include this library our do we
know is really big on libraries it makes
it easy to work with complex thing
like liquid crystal displays right and
what you have to do with this library is
you have to initialize it to che which
pins were connected so where are those
six control lines connected well they're
connected to twelve eleven five four
three and two and you can see that over
here twelve eleven five four three and
two and so that lets us control the LCD
the first thing we have to do is we have
to do a little bit of setup so you have
to tell how many rows and how many
columns are there in your LCD so this
LCD when we start right into it here
it's got sixteen across and then there's
two rooms
I don't like comments so I'm gonna get
rid of this comment just to make my code
look shorter and then it's gonna print a
message to the LCD so when we run this
program I haven't done it yet maybe
you've already done it
it should print hello world right at the
top right that's kind of cool I'm
curious I'm gonna try it so I'm gonna
hit start simulation so as I start the
simulation I sure enough it says hello
world right at the top now the bottom
line just says zero over there to change
into one that's kind of weird
I know it's what's wrong here I'm just
kind of playing and then eventually
it'll change to to what it's doing in
the bottom let's look at their code and
let's see if we can fix it make it
better it says set the cursor to column
zero of line one so column zero of line
one that's the spot right here
so rows this is the top row this is the
the next row and then columns go this
way right and what it's saying is put
the cursor right there and then print to
the LCD some number of milliseconds so
this is how many milliseconds they're
been divided by a thousand
so milliseconds divided by a thousand
should be seconds the reason it wasn't
counting in seconds is because of a bug
let's type some code to fix the bug so
I'm just gonna say fix the bug and to
fix the bug we need to add some kind of
delay to this circuit so type this to
fix the bug add delay one
100 semicolon so this is the first bit
of code we've typed I typed code is much
easier to make little mistakes on right
so for example if you spell the word
delay wrong it doesn't work there's a
parenthesis here maybe I should make my
code even bigger I'll just we'll just
hope you can zoom it out there a
parenthesis and then a 100 and then
another parenthesis and then a semicolon
and if I add that line of code my
simulation should start actually
counting seconds quite nicely so it's
kind of interesting that they gave you
this piece of starter code it kind of
had a bug in it the reason for the bug
was that on their simulator it was
trying to go too fast and it was getting
messed up so we fixed the bug with that
that code so let's go and keep looking
at the code that's in here so it's just
counting seconds down there and what I
want to do is I want to delete some of
these extra comments I just to kind of
clean things up a little and now we can
see how relatively short this piece of
code is now let's make another change
right now it says hello world on the LCD
let's go ahead and change it to where it
has your name on there so I'm going to
change mine to where it says David
Fisher and so now it says David Fisher
and it's counting in in seconds another
fun thing you can do we showed this last
time but at any time if you had a real
board so I'm just gonna take my code
that I've got right now and put it on my
actual breadboard like this is valid
code like the simulator isn't isn't the
joke here so now I can make mine say
David Fisher and it's counting on second
which is nice by the way this fix of the
bug isn't necessary on a real board it's
only necessary because of the simulator
that we're using great so we're
continuing to make improvements which is
kind of fun so it's just kind of
counting away and everything is going
good let's go ahead and let's add
another potentiometer so that we can
display a potentiometer here
instead so that's our goal so let's go
ahead and hide the code and let's go
ahead and add a potentiometer so a
potentiometer is not in the starters
area it's in the basic components area
and so I'm gonna add another
potentiometer now I'm gonna choose to
just plug it right into my breadboard
here because that's how a real
potentiometer would work you just plug
it right into your breadboard and what
I'm gonna do with this bread or this
potentiometer
is I'm going to take terminal one and
I'm gonna hook it up to power and I like
for power lines to be read and now here
it's just kind of shooting right over
the top of all these other things if
that bothers you sometimes I'm OCD is as
you know right you can kind of bend it
to where you can kind of see that it it
does in fact go around all those others
so it connects there and there and then
the other side we're gonna connect to
ground so I'm going to connect from
somewhere somewhere in this row I
noticed that everything that's connected
in this this row is all all connected
together right so it doesn't matter my
potentiometers up there everything in
this row is connected so I've
essentially taken that leg of the
potentiometer and I've connected it
straight to ground now this middle leg
this is going to be our signal line so
our potentiometer similar to theirs
right so it's got power on one side
ground on the other and then their
signal line went here this went to their
contrast and our signal line is going to
go over to our Arduino and we're going
to connect it from here to a zero right
over there you can make it any old color
you like maybe I'll go with a nice
lovely purple shade and then you know if
you want to bend wires you can click on
the wire double click it and you can
kind of like move the move the wires
around so now I am getting a reading
from the middle of my potentiometer and
the way this is set up is with the
potentiometer fully in one direction
you'll get roughly 0 volts and then if
you crank it all the way the other
direction you'll get about 5 volts so
it'll kind of go between these two rails
so right now I've got if it's all the
way this way it's getting about five
volts right now it's getting five volts
to a and zero now an interesting thing
happens in code you would probably
expect those analog readings to be like
between the number zero up to the number
five because that's how many volts it is
but in code it's interesting and this is
because of binary it doesn't go from
zero to five it goes from zero which is
make sense to a number
1023 and 1023 is a special number in
binary it's one less than 1024 and
that's just how they work right so let's
go ahead and play with our codes and see
if we can print that reading to our LCD
so I open up the code so the first thing
that we want to do is we want to set up
a zero as an analog input so this is a
comment you can type the comment if
you'd like I'm just kind of saying what
we're doing but the funny thing about
this is that it's already done
the default for these pins is that they
are analog inputs so normally you do
have to write code to do some setup but
an analog input it's already set up for
you so there's actually no setup that
needs to be done so we can actually just
read the value now the way you read the
value I'm going to go ahead and type
this down in loop is you do analog read
of a zero you can type you can actually
type a zero or two zero I just prefer to
say plain old zero and what this line of
code will do is it will read it but the
way code works it's kind of interesting
reading it but not like saving it
doesn't do anything so what I need to do
is I need to save it off to a variable
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
choose to at the start of my program
like before the setup function up here
I'm going to make a variable this
variable is going to
be an integer variable and an integer
variable is abbreviated with int so int
is short for integer and pot reading pot
is short for potentiometer it's a very
common abbreviation so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to take this variable
called pot reading and I'm gonna put it
in front of my analog read so it's
important to understand what's happening
in code you can you can see what mine is
and you can make yours match but the
important thing is to understand what's
happening here
but it's doing an analog read so like
it's it's getting the value of this pin
and the value is gonna be between 0 to
1023 10:23 means it's at 5 volts and
we're saving it off to that variable now
what I want to do is I'm gonna save off
that variable I'd like to see it on my
screen so what I'm gonna do is right
here instead of printing out mils
divided by a thousand I'm instead gonna
do an LCD print of the pop reading all
right so if I were to run my code now it
would work that have kind of a little
bug in it so let's go ahead and run it
and see what happens by the way if you
never try to run it I'm gonna make an
error on purpose I'm just gonna I'm
gonna leave off this semicolon right so
if you ever try to run it and you've
typed something wrong it'll say sorry it
looks like your code has some errors
it'll try to tell you where the problem
is but usually it'll tell you the line
after the problem right so if you look
at the line that they marked so delay
100 this thing's fine to me look at the
line above it right so oh I probably got
a problem right here and sure enough I'm
missing a semicolon right there right so
I just don't be surprised if you see a
bunch of red it's okay I mean
something's probably typed wrong so what
we should have going on here
let me see if I can make my screen
better is it should be printing was it
not printing it should be printing the
potentiometer reading that's coming from
analog
zero mine doesn't seem to be working why
is it mine working actually it looks
like what I did is this other
potentiometer at some point I was
messing with it this other potentiometer
is the contrast potentiometer and I
can't mess with that right because it'll
mess up your display okay so here is so
mine's working it's got a bug in it
still but it's working and what it says
is showing you the value of the
potentiometer and so as I go higher and
higher it's like as I click this more
and more it's gonna get farther and
farther towards the positive side and
the numbers gonna get bigger and bigger
until you gets to ten twenty three now
here comes the bug you ready if I go
from ten twenty three down I'm gonna
just kind of like click on the middle
here down by like five hundred it looks
like so the real value is 511 it looks
like the value says 511 three and that's
because that three is just still on
there from the ten twenty three right so
the ten twenty three had the value on
there and then when I went to five
eleven that three is still there from
the ten twenty three there's a couple
ways to fix that bug one way to fix that
bug is to clear the LCD you can type
this if you want but I'm going to show
you a better way to do it and if you
clear the LCD it'll it'll fix that bug
so now I can go from ten twenty three
down to like 511 and it'll be fine
the problem with Clear LCD is that my
top line Dave Fisher got wiped off even
though I liked having out there and also
the LCD is kind of flashy so that is one
way to fix it but actually that's not
the way I like to fix it I like to fix
it a much lamer way I like to just print
a couple spaces two or three spaces
should be enough I'll go ahead and do it
three to be thorough and what that does
is let's say that you are displaying a
number like ten twenty three and then so
I'm getting up over a thousand here and
then if you quickly switch down like
five hundred and something it prints the
532 in this case and then a space a
space a space and that clears off those
other ones so that's a very common trick
when you're print
to LCDs just to print a couple spaces
after and it actually turns out to be
much more efficient than LCD clear which
is kind of interesting
sissie houses years going she was
working she's doing great but I do
expect there to be problems problems are
fine pause the video hopefully you can
look at my code hopefully it's big
enough now and you can try to get yours
work so analog readings are neat we can
we can see different analog reading
values which is cool but I'd like for
this analog reading to do something
right so I wanted to control something
and what I decided it would be fun to
control is a servo motor so let's go
ahead and see if we can add a servo
motor to our circuit so we've done LCDs
potentiometers now we're gonna do servos
the service you can scroll around
there's two servos in here some one for
some reason there's a blue one and then
there's a black one somewhere else so I
want the blue one I don't want to see
right now which is good and so my servo
it's fine right where it's at or if you
want to you can rotate it around some
I'm gonna rotate mine around to where
it's this direction for no real reason
it's just kind of where I felt like
doing it and a servo motor works like
this it's got a signal line which comes
to the microcontroller power and ground
so power we know where connect power we
connect that to our red rail and then
just because I want to I'm gonna choose
to make that wire be read again the wire
color doesn't mean anything but it can
help make your circuit easier for others
to understand the one that's labeled
ground I'm going to connect to the black
ground rail so I connected ground to the
black ground rail and I connected the
middle one which was power to the red
power rail now this last one which is
called signal I'm gonna have to take it
over to my microcontroller and what I'm
going to do is I'm going to shoot it
what the heck I was kind of shoot it
over the top here I'm gonna go to pen
there's nothing sacred about pen 9 but
it is one that definitely works and you
can make that color I'll be whatever you
want maybe I'll use a white wire maybe
why it's not very visible but you can
see that there's my there's my white
wire so I'm gonna control this servo
motor from pen 9 so it's interesting
that like I said I was gonna control
with the potentiometer but really the
potentiometer goes to the
microcontroller and the servo goes to
the microcontroller and that way the
microcontroller is in charge of
everything right so yeah the
potentiometer controlling it but really
it's all via the microcontroller cool so
that's the wiring that we need to add
for a servo motor by the way if you ever
just wanted to learn about servo motors
we're not doing this now that I'm just
mentioning it there are some starters
with servo motors in here and you could
so there's one right there and you could
use that it's kind of like learning
about the code some but we're just gonna
do it together so let's go learn about
servo motors so servo motors are not
extremely complex but they're a little
complex they are complex enough that
it's kind of nice to use code that
somebody else wrote so type this with me
at the top so we're gonna use code that
somebody else rooms
whenever you use somebody else's code
you have to do what's called an include
into your program and so we're gonna say
pound it's just sound like a little
hashtag symbol pound include servo dot H
so the liquid crystal we got that code
for free because whenever we brought in
the starter it gave us the code but it
shows you the style that we need for a
servo and then similar to what we did
for liquid crystal we created a variable
of type liquid crystal so here we
created an invariable here we created a
liquid crystal and then right in between
the two I'm gonna create a variable for
my servo not being very creative with
names I'm gonna name my variable my
circle so hopefully you can see the form
out here it goes what type of variable
is it and then what's the name of the
variable so this one wasn't
Boult int variable it's what's called a
primitive variable type and it was
called pop reading this one was a liquid
crystal variable and the name of that
variable is LCD and you can see that
it's a fancy variable I can do stuff
right so it's an object and then this
one is my servo it's also a fancy
variable and it has stuff it can do as
well by the way this line right here is
what's called a constructor so we're
constructing a variable called my servo
of type servo now in the same way that
we did things like LCD begin an LCD
print we can do things with my servo my
servo has a couple different things that
can do one thing is you can say what pin
you want it to attach to now how do I
know these magic commands in fact I'm
not sure that attach is the right word
I'm gonna have to go look it up but the
way you know commands like this is
through coding reference guides now you
can you can navigate here with me or you
can just watch for a minute but how do I
know that that command is attached well
then no the way you know things is you
go to the arduino reference guide and i
just started typing in our tweener
reference and mine auto-completed
and it's got all the different functions
that you can use with an arduino and
it's also got here in libraries
different libraries that you can use
with arduino for example here's liquid
crystal here is servo and so if you go
into servo you can see that it gives you
a couple little examples which are nice
and it tells you what the functions are
like attached and right you can also
read things and in fact one of their
examples is called knob this is actually
really close to what we're building here
so it's a potentiometer circuit that's
controlling a servo and these examples
are great because they'll actually like
show you the code to make this thing
work and you'll notice that in their
code here they've got the include line
they call there's my servo that's where
I stole the name from and then they do
some other things that we're also going
to do but we'll do it
kind of one piece at a time all right so
let's go back to our code and we'll keep
working so back in our code we've
attached the servo so we've told this
servo object where it's connected to so
it's connected to pin nine now we want
to do things with that servo so let's go
ahead and in the loop let's just try a
couple things let's try my servo dot
right let's send it to zero and then
wait for a full second I'm gonna type
this fast and then you can then you can
get caught up servo I have a little s my
variable name and then I'm gonna do
write 180 and wait for a second I might
even wait for two seconds here so I
wrote that fast because it's sometimes
easier to finish it and then let you
pause the video and then type of
yourself so I'm going to say control the
servo so see if you can add that code
and then try it out alright so let's try
it out so I zoomed in a little bit here
so when I run it what should happen is
my servo should start at zero so you
should kind of like sit there for two
seconds and then it should start wiping
back and forth which is cool and so you
can also by the way you can try this on
a real board as well so if I take this
code and I paste it over here and I put
it on to my real board now it wants its
programmed up here what should happen is
it should just make the servo just go
back and forth from 0 to 180 so a servo
motor doesn't spin all the way around
there kind of a different style of motor
they're designed to go from 0 to 180
degrees just wherever you tell them to
go so there's different types of motors
that do different things and you'll
notice that the analog reading is still
showing up on my display here but the
servo isn't using it yet so that's our
next goal is we've kind of got a servo
that's working and an analog reading
that's working and we're gonna put them
together right also go ahead and set
this guy over here I'm gonna have to
unplug him or else he's gonna really
annoy
me so I'll plug unplug him there so
let's go ahead and try to get these two
things working together so what I really
want to do is I want to take this pop
reading and I want to use it to control
the servo now if I just so I'm going to
show you something that doesn't really
work so I'm going to comment these four
lines out these were just kind of for my
testing I'm so I'm going to comment this
out what I want to do is I want to just
take my servo and write to it the pot
reading I would love to do that the
problem is the pot reading goes from 0
to 1023 and the servo goes from 0 to 180
right so if I did this
it wouldn't work because it would work
at the bottom right but as soon as the
potentiometer gets up over 180 so as
soon as it's like 2 or 3 or 400 great
it's not going to work right so we've
got to do is we've got to scale the pot
reading back now one thing that you
could kind of sort of do this does work
but it's not not what we're going to do
is you could divide it by some number to
make it smaller right so if you were to
just divide it by some number to make it
smaller that would scale it I think that
divided by 6 would roughly work you know
what I'm curious enough to try it what
I'm gonna do is I'm gonna write to the
servo divided by 6 and I'm gonna also
print out that value just so I know what
I'm sending to my servo I don't let me
give it a shot
so right now it says Dave Fischer 170
and it's 170 because it's really 10 23
divided by 6 an interesting thing
happens with microcontrollers is 10 23
divided by 6 should be a fraction right
so it should be like this crazy decimal
it just truncates it to the nearest
integer value it's just how it works so
when it's 10 23 divided by 6 that should
be 170 I haven't done the math but I'm
sure the top must work out and then if I
move to like the middle then my servo
follows that and then if I move all the
way up to the end of the range it goes
there so I can
my servo with this code and now again
just because I enjoy doing it I could
switch to driving this on a real board
as well so if I wanted to I could run
this on my actual factual board and I
could see the the servo moving back and
forth as I moved the potentiometer which
is kind of cool so now it's got my
potentiometer reading displayed on here
divided by six and as I turn this knob
you can see that it turns the
potentiometer as well and it actually
works it works pretty neat sis did you
get yours working yes cool so I think
that that is a pretty neat thing to do
that's almost the end of the exercise
for today now there is a special like
magic command in Arduino that can do
this conversion from like 0 to 1023 to 0
to 180 perfectly and it's called map so
it's just one of the functions that's
built into Arduino we'll go ahead and
try it out so what we're gonna need
first is we're gonna need another
variable by the way make sure you always
top your simulation before you try to
type I'm sure that everybody has done
this but if you try to type when you're
still in the middle of a simulation it
won't do anything so I'll tell I'll make
a new variable I'll call it Dec dag is
short for degrees
I couldn't type degrees but I feel lazy
today so I'm just gonna type beg for
degrees all right so now I've got this
new variable dig and what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna say dag is equal to map and
what we're gonna do is we're gonna map
that pot reading which normally goes
from 0 to 1023 into a new range from 0
to 180 and so this is this special
function map does that's called linear
interpolation for you so take this
reading which goes from 0 to 1023 and
map it to a new value that goes from 0
to 180 and now what I can do is instead
of doing pot reading divided by 6 which
was a pretty good
approximation I'm just gonna print out
deck and then I'm gonna also used egg to
write to my servo and now what should
happen is dag should very accurately go
from zero to 180 now before it was going
from zero to 170 personally that was
pretty darn good but now at 10:23 it
should go to 180 and then if I go all
the way down to zero I goes there and it
should go everywhere in between
so obviously map is better than divide
by six but to be honest divided by six
it's pretty darn good cool so that is a
map and that's actually the end so I
think that this is a pretty good place
to call it good
I suppose the the final thing I should
probably put onto my board and we should
be able to see this thing going back and
forth now I do encourage you to play
some with this and so like one thing
that I played with so now it goes from
zero so actually it's at 180 right now
all the way down to two zero cool so I
do encourage you to play with this if
you remember my solution I did some
other goofing around things I'd love for
you to goof around some more one thing
that I did is I added three servo motors
I just kind of Fergus I make them all
get controlled by pin nine you can also
this this is an optional extra you can
try to write some code here I'm using a
for loop that kind of like smoothly goes
from zero to 180 I'm not gonna work this
with you but if you did want to do
something like this this is an extra
thing that you could build on your own
that I would love for you to to try to
do to make yours better
alright that's all we got for today
hopefully you learned about analog
readings potentiometers LCD displays and
servo motors we look forward to seeing
you tomorrow we'll do some other stuff
hopefully you got some good hands-on
experience with with typing code I am
sure that you made a lot more buttons
than me
and you got some practice
debugging practice with debugging is
super important so don't feel bad when
you see that read that's that's you
learning right so so red is good all
right we will see you tomorrow thanks so
much for joining us
[Music]